So, we're going to get started. I'm
calling the uh March
11th traffic commission meeting to
order. Thank you very much for all
joining. We have a we have a uh one or
two people who are not present but we do
have a quorum. So we are going to go
forward. The first item on the agenda is
the minutes of the previous meeting.
the January meeting.
I'll make a motion to approve the
January
uh 2025 meeting minutes. I'll second.
So, there's been a motion in a second.
Is there any further discussion?
Hearing none. All in favor say I. I. I.
Any opposed? The motion carries. Thank
you very much.
The next item is staff project updates.
Um Cindy, do we have any of those that
we want to share?
Um yes, we have um I'm not sure if they
were distributed or not, Mindy, the the
update. Um yes, we have sort of a
spreadsheet that we're um providing each
month to the commission related to
various projects that the um public
works is working on related to um
streets and um in in the city.
So last month I provided um a
spreadsheet that includes a list of the
projects that we're currently working
on. Um I can just go through a couple of
these just to highlight things that have
changed since the last meeting.
um the Ann and Juniata uh streetscape
project. Um we did receive uh some
additional funding for that project. So
we now have close to a million dollars.
Um and we are kicking off with a
consultant uh later this month to
identify what the scope uh what we can
include with that you know that kind of
funding in the scope. So again, that was
a lot of safety improvement, you know, a
safety improvement at the Ann and
Juniata intersection and then also
looking at improving sidewalks and
lighting uh in that area on Juniata and
um An Street.
um the Manor Street traffic signal
project. If we go down um halfway
through the uh the list there, we are
currently under construction um for that
and that's replacing traffic signals at
New Delwood um Pearl and uh Ruby and um
along Matter Street. So, we're updating
the traffic signals and that's happening
right now. Um the Plum Street
roundabout, I know the commission
received information about a sign that
was knocked down there. um that project,
you know, that sign has it um we may
replace it with some other uh
delineators because the sign keeps
getting hit. Um I know if you've been
out to Plum Street, the the work isn't
quite complete. They had to shut down
for the winter um and signs and pavement
markings weren't all completely
installed or and the paving actually. So
hopefully in the next month or two,
those will all be um in installed and
you'll see a completed project out
there.
um the Queen and Farnum intersection
improvement. That's where we're adding
some bumpouts, um some a flashing
beacons, and we're also doing some green
infrastructure at that intersection.
That will be going out to bid um in the
next month or so. So, that will be under
construction this summer. And then the
South Duke Street mobility project where
we are
um doing improvements along South Duke
Street in including a shared use path
along the side of South Duke and adding
back in diagonal parking on the west
side of the street and trying to improve
a lot of the pedestrian crossings in
that area that um we received bids
today. So we'll be reviewing those and
hopefully awarding that in the next
month or so. So construction will start
on South Duke Street as well. And then
um just to highlight the street design
guidelines and the two-way conversion.
Those were all uh those are both
projects related to the safe streets for
all grant that we received and we are
kicking those off. Um so we should be
going out to the public probably in the
June um early summer time frame with
some preliminary analysis and um
discussion with the public about those
projects. And then finally the um
residential permit parking program. We
are working with LPA uh to collect
occupancy data. They have the license
plate reader equipment that um is being
tested and once we have more information
related to the occupancy data. So
knowing how much parking is being used
during specific time periods um then
we'll be able to go out uh back out to
the public for those pilot areas that
were identified and um start to have
discussion about how to address RP in
those areas.
Very good. Thank you very much. Are
there any questions from the on the
commission on any of these
projects and Cindy, you had said that
the this is available on the website as
well? Is this updated on the website? Um
I don't believe it's um available on the
website, but that is something we could
provide on the um vision zero website.
Actually, we could add that to the
vision zero website. In many ways, we're
we're looking at this as an enhancement
of another way to communicate with the
public on what is going on and what is
being done in the public right of way.
So,
um if if we can do that, that would be
great. Um and I thank you for the for
the
update. Next, we'll go to the action
agenda. The first item is old business
item
512024 considering the request of Kevin
Ralphs to add a con I'm sorry of Kevin
Ralphs to add a convex mirror to the
intersection of North Plum Street and
Reynolds Avenue. Is Mr. Ralphs
present? Ben, is this something that
you're updating us on? So staff member
Ben Hogan will be updating us.
Oh.
[Applause]
Good afternoon, commission. Uh my name
is Ben Hogan. I'm a public works
engineer for city of Lancaster. So this
one uh Plum and Reynolds was before you
at the last meeting. Um, this is looking
at the initial request was for a convex
safety mirror to see approaching traffic
because of a sight distance issue. Uh,
we no longer install convex safety
mirrors. It's not an approved treatment.
So, we looked at some parking removal
instead to get adequate sight lines at
this intersection. Um, last time we had
proposed removing some parking at the
intersection, particularly 40 ft on the
north side on the northwest corner and
about 36 1/2 ft on
the southeast corner for adequate
visibility. Uh, the commission had
requested more public outreach. So,
since the last meeting, we've reached
out to residents within a uh twob block
area radius of this intersection that
might travel through or park at the
intersection. We sent letters to both
property owners and tenants in English
and Spanish. I got one response. I
provided them with my email, phone
number, and an invitation to today's
meeting. Uh the one response I did get
was um a resident that lived about a
block away on Marshall Street, and she
was uh she um was with our idea. She
wanted to see parking removed to have
improved visibility. So, I didn't
receive any other public comment. Um
just looking for your action at this
time if you feel it's appropriate to
implement this restriction.
Um Mindy, are you able to turn this so
that we can see the actual intersection?
And Sergeant and Philip, you can move up
this so that you can see the the the
diagrams close up to
you. Very good. Thank you.
So, Ben, you're you're
proposing where this blue car is that
that would be.
Yes, we would take parking back to uh
where that existing sign post is right
now. It's around 36 1/2 ft to that
existing signpost. Uh about 1 and 1/2
parking spaces. Um and then on the north
side of that intersection, we're
proposing to take 40 ft um for adequate
visibility. And we're also considering
adding a pedestrian crossing there in
the future. Uh there's a ramp on the
other side that's already been
constructed. So we just need to
construct one on this side. And that
parking restriction would line up nicely
if we chose to uh move forward with that
in the future.
So in essence that's um in order to
provide that kind of visibility we we'd
be losing approximately three and a half
spaces total. Yes.
Um are there any questions from the
commission or disc further discussion
about the sidewalk from the commission?
Uh you mentioned that in the future you
might add another ramp and a and a
crosswalk. Is that a future project just
because it involves more cost than
putting up the sides or Yeah, there's a
few complications here. There's a tree
at that corner that's very close to the
corner that might need some work.
There's also a storm water inlet there.
Whenever we're adding ramps, we have to
consider when we lower the curb also
moving those inlets. So, it can add up
to be quite a bit of cost. Um, we
certainly want to finish that pedestrian
crossing. Um, just looking to add that
to a future contract. Um that's not not
exactly lined up at this time.
Okay. Have we looked at any of the uh
accident data for that? We
have uh yeah so we looked at reportable
crash data over the past five years. Uh
the five available years were 2019 to
the end of 2023. There were two
reportable crashes at the intersection.
Um, both incidents involve vehicles on
Reynolds Avenue proceeding without
clearance into the intersection. Uh, so
that kind of supported our our
initiative to improve sight lines at the
intersection. It seems like those
incidents could have been resolved by
improved sight lines.
Any further
questions? Any
recommendations?
Any
motions? Excuse it. Can I move that we
adopt the recommendation to remove the
parking spots? Yes, you may. All right.
I move that we adopt the recommendation
to remove the parking spots. There's a
motion. Is there a second? Second. A
motion and a second. Is there any
further discussion at the commission
level? At the level of the public. Is
anyone from the public want to speak on
this item?
Hearing none. All in favor of of
approving what's been proposed by uh
staff say I. I. Any opposed? The motion
carries. Thank you very very much. Thank
you. The next item under old business is
item 02 of 2025. Considering the request
of Jason Staer of Ecklund Development to
add a load zone to either 2-8 South Duke
Street or 46 East King Street. Mr.
Ster. Um Ben, is this something that
your you and your team have taken a look
at? Has it? No, we've not Oh, yeah. I
mean, I think it's been reviewed. Was
the Did we get an official request?
for sure. I think it was reviewed by
police previously
was reviewed by in the minutes from the
last meeting, right? Yeah, it was
reviewed by previously.
I think the recommendation was deni
denied and then the the requester wasn't
present at the last meeting. So,
correct. So, I think I
Mr. Stford was not in attendance.
Sergeant Trace stated that he denied
this loading zone during site review and
stated why. Director Campbell asked if
staff had looked at at it. Miss
McCormick stated yes, but she thought it
should wait until Mr. Staer was in
attendance. So, he's currently not in
attendance. We should continue to table
this one.
I'll make a motion to table. A motion to
table. Second and a second. Any further
discussion? All in favor? How many
meetings can they not show up for until
it's eliminated? Eliminate like the
request is taken off anymore. The
question is how many meetings do does it
get tabled for before we just remove it
because they're not in attendance?
Correct. Um it's a matter of internal
policy I would imagine twice. Right. So
this would remove would remove it from
the agenda and the person could um
submit resubmit at a later date.
So we're giving them the opportunity,
right? We're saying they if they don't
show up for the next meeting, it would
be denied and then
they right. So they already missed too.
Yes. This is the second one that they've
missed. Okay.
So do we want to just deny it?
and have them resubmit.
Sure. Yes, we're in support of
that. Two two
no-shows means a
denial and then the person is still free
to
resubmit, but um it does not stay alive.
And if if someone has missed two uh two
meetings in a row, so then I would
revise my
um motion to deny the application 02
2025. So the the previous motion has
been withdrawn. The new motion is to
deny. Is there a second? Second. Denial
and a second. A motion and a second. Any
further discussion? All in favor? I. Any
opposed? Not opposed. Motion carries.
This motion is
denied. Okay. Now we're back. Now we're
into new
business. The first item is item 09
2025 considering the request from the
Lancaster Maria at Penn Square to renew
the designated parking spaces on East
King for hotel use. And the requesttor
is Mr. Josh Novak. Yes, Mr. Novak. Yes.
Um, good afternoon. I'm Josh Novak. I'm
the general manager for the Lancaster
Marriott and Lancaster County Convention
Center. before you as the agenda
indicated is the renewal um for
utilization of the parking spots uh
designated parking spots there on East
King Street right in front of the hotel
and plow restaurant um as uh activity at
the hotel and convention center
continues to increase these spots are
really imperative um to help accommodate
uh arriving guests for both the hotel uh
and events. Uh as you know if you've
been downtown um our driveway is a bit
limited. So when there are heavy
activity going on there um these spots
are uh very very important for us to
help unload guests and uh those who are
arriving um to the facility. It also
cuts down tremendously on volume of cars
who are coming up Queen Street towards
Penn who are in that turning lane
waiting to turn into the driveway. So,
uh, we have been leasing them from the
Lancaster Parking Authority, uh, and it
continues to be a very important area
for us,
and it is currently legally a loading
zone.
Yeah. I mean, yes, we un I don't know
the official designation of it, but it
we use it for loading and unloading. I
saw the no parking and I didn't Yeah, it
is not it's not used to park. It's it's
for loading and unloading. and we are a
24-hour business, so this happens um
around the clock. Very good. Um are
there any questions or further
discussion from the commission regarding
this request?
Anything that we need to be aware of? I
guess my yeah my question would be is it
is it is the 247
still necessary or
um because obviously yeah during the
daytime um there's a lot of businesses
along that block. Um
yeah the answer I would say is is
absolutely yes. Uh it's hard to predict
depending on the composition of events
or weekends or things that are going on
at the hotel. um when the heaviest
arrivals are. In a lot of cases, um many
times we have the entire hotel checking
out and the entire hotel checking in. Uh
and that can take, you know, throughout
the evening. So there's not it's very
it's not uncommon for me or anybody they
say six or seven where we would still
have two to
300 rooms set to still arrive.
So, it's very hard to predict based on
the composition of what's going on
throughout the year.
And besides the um the circle in and
this this loading zone, is there uh
opportunity at the um at the parking
garage to to load as well? Yeah. Yes, we
we certainly do that as well. Um, but
that driveway, as you probably know, is
really probably fits four to five cars
cuz you keep a lane open for obviously
emergency services. So, it's sort of an
extension of the driveway and, you know,
very critical. Okay. I think your
question was from the park garage, not
from the driveway. from the park. No, I
so I we do as much as we can um because
we don't have valet services, we do
direct people to go right to the
Pensquare garage if they're checking in.
That's just not a reality depending on
the amount of luggage, the age of the
guests who are arriving. So, we do try
to do that as much as we can.
Okay.
Any questions, comments, suggestions,
recommendations?
Is there a particular reason why you do
not do valet parking?
Um, it's still something that's still in
in consideration postco. Um, being able
to staff it. Um, but it it would still
require us to use those areas even more
so now that we have the additional
tower. Mhm. So now that we're 416
rooms, it would that would be even more
queuing for valet services for sure.
I would just say as somebody who has
used a hotel, I might not have read it
ahead of time that I'm supposed to go in
the garage and probably would park out
front initially until I went in and got
instructions. So that doesn't surprise
me that even if you're trying to get
folks to go in the garage, they're not
going to do it right away.
Any further
questions? Um, is there a potential
motion?
I'll make a motion to um approve the
request for the Lancaster Marriott at
Pence Square for renewal of their
designated parking space on East King
Street for hotel purposes. There's been
a motion to approve.
Is there a second? I have a second. A
motion and a second. Is there further
discussion at the commission level?
I would just like to add that um I
believe it was three years. Was that the
time frame for is it two or three?
Three would be fine. I think the
stipulation from previous approvals was
that this needed to be renewed every
three years. So I I think it would be
prudent to add that as well. So So we're
adding that it's renew
it's valid for three years would require
renewal after the third year.
So in March 2028. Yes.
Any further discussion?
Any discussion from the public? Parking
authority supports the request.
I'm sorry. Parking authority supports
the request. Okay. Very good. Thank you.
Um hearing none. Any um all in favor? I.
Any opposed? The motion carries. Thank
Thank you very much.
The next item under new business is item
10, 2025, considering the request of a
load zone at Segro Airport, 358 to 360
North Queen Street.
Isopro,
hello everybody. Hi. How are you? I'm
reading the notes here from uh Sergeant
Drace
uh which I thought he was going to be
here tonight and uh just just those
people know um Sergeant Sergeant Drace
has retired and and Sergeant Solor Doris
Sallall has has is happily joined us to
take his place. Well, he looks like a
good man to be on this board.
And uh I originally thought the vote was
supposed to be a handicap and one
loading zone space. And when they did
it, they only put in the handicap space.
I think it's been made clear
um to you what the what we were putting
in as far as a handicap space. Well, it
says it right in here in the notes. It
was a a loading zone. It was a handicap
and one parking space. In what? In in
the minutes.
I think there was then it was a made
note that it needed to be a discussion
for you to coordinate with staff after.
Yes. And I think we made it clear it was
either a handicap space or a loading
zone that we were willing that's that's
not what I understood and that's even
what I even called Ben
about about the loading zone.
Um, I think we talked about the fact
that there was going to be a loading
zone on Lemon Street and that is why
Well, I sent you pictures of the loading
zone on Prince Street.
Yeah. So, has anybody looked at them?
The the improvements related to the bike
facility aren't complete yet. There will
be delineators that will be put in the
area.
Excuse me. That became a
four lane parking space up there. And
that and that was a three today and
there's four there right now. The fire
engine couldn't even turn to get down or
tractor and trailer cannot turn at that
street right
[Music]
now. I've had loading zones for 65
years.
and all of a sudden um we're not using
correctly, the whole block uses it.
So the fact that the whole block uses it
when is not was not the issue and I'm
paying for it.
Why why was it taken away? And why is
our why is our push back 20 feet 9 in
and on the other side of the street is
146. Why Why can't it be
even? I'm just
rereading the minutes.
It does state that the way Mr. Seo is is
using the loading zone is not the
intended purpose. On the application
which was shown to the audience, it
stated that any vehicle that is in the
process of actively loading or unloading
of property may utilize the load zones.
Starting three stated that this is not
how Mr. Cedro is using the load zone. He
also offered to remove the load zone and
place a handicap parking space. Sergeant
Drace made a motion to accept items 05
2025 and 06 2025 of the consent agenda
seconded by Mr. Mandros. When I talked
to Sergeant Drece, he never said that to
me and I called the mayor's office on
it. They would not recall. So now it's
we went to the district attorney's
office on this subject.
So and where and if you've gone to the
district attorney's office where
everybody we're talk we're talk
discussion because Sergeant Dre told me
something completely different. He said
it was not up to him and he came out and
spoke against me here when I called when
I called when this all happened. So,
I don't know why after 41 years, nobody
on the block ever
complained and all of a sudden, uh,
there's a person complaining. I'm not
complaining about loading zones that are
24/7, 7 days a
week. I'm not asking for something like
that, which there are in the city.
I'm not asking for a loading zone in
front of the liquor control store, which
they they load from the side. So, it's
all it's all retail, right? So, if
somebody loses our loading
zone, which I pay for, and goes to
Lancaster Pickle Company, that's not
that's not good. If you can't get a
parking space on the block, they can't
use a meter. So, these loading zones are
not I mean, please correct me if I'm
wrong. The loading zones are not for
handicap parking. No, we have one of
those. Right. And that was So we
corrected that last time by adding a
handicap space.
So I guess here's my challenge. I'm
looking at what was in the minutes and
it seems to coincide with my
recollection of what was discussed and
then you've you've gone outside to get a
different reading. Is that what I'm
understanding? No, I I thought just as
the the minutes I thought it was
supposed it was it was instead of two
spaces, it was it got reduced to a
handicap space and a loading zone space.
If I remember the last meeting
correctly, I think that the ultimately
the request was
withdrawn at the meeting and then it
looks like in the intro there's been a
new request that was handled
administratively for a handicap parking
spot which has been installed and then
another request for a load zone and I
see um that the recommendation from uh
Sergeant Summer I believe was to deny it
because it seems like a more appropriate
space for a load zone would be mid
block, right? So, you're putting the
loading zone that people use
uh on Lemon Street. So, when the
purveyors that go to the Belvadier, they
have to cross two intersections now.
Well, it's to be put it's to be put in a
location that tries to serve as many
businesses as possible. There's no
business on Lemon Street.
There's only there's a there's a lady
that does
hair and there and there's a
store. That's the only businesses on
Lemon Street. So, the recommendation is
not for Lemon Street. The recommendation
is to move the loading zone south on
Queen Street. It's to move it south.
Can you pull up the picture? No. South
would be Yes, I guess if you want to
call it south. Yeah. So there is even
another loading zone space at Lemon and
uh
Duke which is not even used anymore
that's used for uh going to the uh
funerals and dentist offices and and
places like that. That's not loading and
unloading
either. So you have two you have four
car parking space on Lemon Street that
has no businesses.
[Music]
Basically the your request to add a
loading zone Yes ma'am. was reviewed by
the police and they
indicated that the location you
requested would be denied, but their
recommendation was if a loading zone was
needed on that block on the 300 block of
North Queen Street that it should be mid
block. Put it on mid
block. We need a loading zone. Okay. And
that that's what I guess we can discuss.
And it should be on our side because
that's where all the businesses are and
that's the safest place to get off is
right onto the payment.
So mid block would be closer to uh the
guild or you know somewhere in that
that's fine just as long as we have a
loading zone. We have Airbnbs, we got
antique shops, we got uh u pickle shops,
we got uh nail nail nail salons. They
all get they all get shipments.
So, it has not been executed as yet.
Correct. What what people are used to is
they're used to the loading zone at this
location. That's why I said it' be more
convenient and I'd be willing to pay for
it.
So, I guess I have a procedural question
because the the report from the request
says that a more appropriate location
would be in block. You know, it's not
like I come to meetings all the time, so
I don't know what the requests were or
how it got changed. That's okay. We're
we're all trying to make it clear, but
but I did after after the final summary
of all this went down, which I was very
new at, uh I thought it was a handicap
and adding the loading zone
uh to the behind the handicap section.
When Travis Good came to our place, he
said uh when they were putting the the
uh the 20.9
setback. Uh he said they would probably
add the uh two parking spaces behind
that and that you know that calmed us
down you know I mean we were all
upset you know without notice and
everything else that's happened to
us I think it's not the right way to do
business and I think we should be
treating businesses in Lancaster a
little bit better than what we're doing
here. If I may, I just want to ask if if
there's already been a recommendation
that a midblock load zone might be
appropriate, do we need
to do this as a as a commission or or
just as a administrative clarification?
Yeah, if that if that's already seems
appropriate, then do we need to not do
anything? Why not why not put it back
where it was originally?
Can I ask that question? Just for may I
ask let me give you a point of reference
that'll help you guys. Can you just come
to the background?
Larry Cohen, parking
authority. Uh, there was a midblock
loading zone that was paid for by
building characters. They had it for
several years. Marty gave it up, I think
at least over a year
ago, because he stated that folks were
just parking there and it wasn't being
used as a loading zone. So, I just want
to let you know whatever decision you
make, there was a mid block pretty much
in front of building characters. Um, of
course, we need to enforce it, right? So
that folks are not just parking there,
right? But in the recent past there was
and it was given up by the uh building
characters who paid for it. So, I just
want to let you know that. Thank you. So
in essence, the the recommendation is to
is to revert back to having that loading
zone basically in the same location that
it previously had been in. I mean, it
helps because that's everybody knows it.
The people from out of town, they know
it. They go to the Belvadier, the the
meat guys, the booze guys, you know,
they all go there. So, it's convenient.
Our our guys know it. All all the uh
uh all the postmen, all the uh drop off
guys of the pickle shop and all that,
they're all there. All of the Korean
restaurants, they drop they park down
there and put their uh uh food bring
their food up to the restaurant. Yeah,
it's I mean it you know and with that
loading zone and it's safer there
restored then we just need to make sure
that it is enforced properly so that it
is available for loading as necessary.
You're you're referring to the mid block
loading zone mid block. I just want to
make that clear. I don't believe that's
what I was referring to when you were
speaking or what he was understanding. I
think that's what Mr. Con said too. The
midlock didn't work. I I don't think he
said that. He said that cars were
parking there. Um, but that's something
that can be enforced as well. Yeah, it's
an enforcement issue. Oh, sure. Sure. I
mean, we've got the people got tickets
there. Sure. So, had it been Had just a
second. Had it been removed, had that
loading zone been removed or was it just
not enforced? You need me to come up?
So Marty from building characters had
made the request for that loading zone
midb block on Queen and he m he paid for
it over the however many years and
within the last year or two he said he
did not want to pay for the mid for the
loading zone anymore. So the mid block
loading zone was removed. Correct. Okay.
So the request then is for it to be
restored or for there to be a new
midblock loading zone put in put in
there. Well, that wasn't the original
request, but if you're modifying that
request, request if you want to just
asking for clarity of what the request
is at this point. That's not my request.
The clarification was that I would the
loading zone would be put back behind
the handicap zone.
So you would probably deny that request
and approve a reinstitution of the midb
block which nobody wants.
Well, we have to we have to enforce it,
right? For sure. Um, and I just want to
clarify the the loading zone was in
front of Mad Cap, not in building
character. Yeah, it was somewhere in
that it was in front of Mad Cap. Mad.
That's one that's gone, but it was there
like not long ago,
right? Yeah, that's where the location I
think Marty was paying for that loading
zone. That's a whole another
conversation, but I don't think it's
gone though. It It is. Is it?
So, the situation that we want to have
is what which is consistent with either
what had been recommended or with the
need. Well, I guess the first question
is to Mr. Seg if if he wants to proceed
uh would you would it be acceptable to
have a mid block loading zone one that's
farther south than what you initially
requested? I'm sorry I can't I I I'm not
understanding you. Would it would it
meet your needs to have a loading zone
that's further south than what your
initial request was? I understand your
initial request was one for one that's
directly south of what's now the
handicap parking spot and the
recommendation was to deny that. So that
would would be the ideal one because uh
if you want to take a poll of all the uh
So I understand that that's okay. Would
you accept would it be would it meet
your needs to have one that's a little
bit further south
and that's towards uh the old lepers or
reinstated
at the more action is down this way
because they they can hit the bell over
there. They can hit the store across the
street. They can hit uh all the antiques
and they can hit the uh gallery and they
change over. They can hit the pop-up
shop and they change constantly. So,
would you rather not have a load zone
and have one further south? I would
rather bring it back to where it was for
41 years. That that's not an option at
this point. Pardon me. That's not the
option that's being presented at this
point. that was denied based on a site
review done by myself as well as
traffic.
So would you be okay with it being why
why why would all of a sudden would it
be denied? Your your last request or
application has been put in for a load
zone in front of your property. Um I
believe it's was it 58? Was it 358? It
was already there for 41 years. It was
taken away without it's not there now
and we're going based on now and the
application that was put in it was it
was Am I putting the application in
wrong? No, you're not putting it in.
Okay. Site review has to be completed
which it was and that and that site
review uh done by more than one person
does not recommend a vote zone be placed
where you're requesting it. I understand
that that would be most convenient for
you. Okay. However, that is not an
approved recommendation. Okay. Well, how
do I get a loading zone for the block?
So, that's what we're talking about now.
We're presenting to you the option of
possibly moving and putting a loading
zone south of where you're requesting
it. I I I said let's go for it. Okay.
And that's that's the question he was
asking, but I said the ideal one and
then I we get that we we understand
exactly
We're all trying to get to the same
place, I think. Um, so the intention
would be to
to implement a loading zone further
south approximately where can we show
it? Is it exactly in front of these
buildings or approximately where? I
guess would you have to should we do
another assessment? Yes, we should do
and identify. So I think
If that's the case, then it could be
handled like a typical loading zone in
that you're identifying I mean in this
situation we're identifying the optimal
location, but it would be done
administratively and then it would just
come before the the commission as a
consent agenda item.
That's and that would that would be the
loading
zone and there would still be a handicap
parking space. Correct. That is that is
that has been installed and I believe
it's on the consent agenda.
That has been installed. The handicap.
Yes. I biked by earlier and I saw it. It
looks nice. Pardon me. I biked by
earlier and I saw the hand. Looks nice.
So, you did the right thing by
requesting clarification and
confirmation. And uh although it's not
exactly where you had hoped for it to
be, what we're about to act on is likely
getting you I shouldn't I shouldn't
presume the vote, but uh is there any
further discussion? I I don't know what
Please tell me what what just happened.
Go over it one more time and what what's
going to happen?
So there it's it's a report another
report would be done to confirm that
site review site review will be done to
confirm that it's appropriate for it to
be in that location or in the proposed
closer to midblot location. Okay. And
can I just confirm that another request
doesn't need to be made? Is that right?
We'll just handle it as the same. I was
that's okay. that that with that report
with confirmation it would be done
administratively and would be uh under
the consent the consent actions next
time as work that will have been done.
So when when the approvals are made
administratively it doesn't need to come
before the commission staff just does
that. So in this case, it's police and
our traffic um unit will review it and
identify the best location and then they
can have it installed based on their
recommendation and then it just comes to
us sort of post after it's been
installed for a a formal approval so
that it's documented in the books
basically. Well, the communications
between the traffic commission and the
individual, there's no emails going back
and forth. There's no you can't get
anybody to talk to you. all the I could
never I I got Ben accidentally. He
picked a phone up accidentally to call
out and I was on the line and I I had to
tell him that his his mailbox was full.
He said there's no way to Huh. I
appreciated that. And he said there's no
way to tell. So if you call the mayor's
office, their mailbox is full. Sergeant
Drace always answered whenever you
called. He was always on the ball there.
But you know, other places are not. But
I still got I still want an answer on
the uh setback of 20.9 to the other
setback on the other side of 14.6. Why
why the difference? Can somebody answer
that question here? Well, 20 20 ft from
crosswalk is
the is what is allow or what is required
by law. So we can look at the other
side. I'm not sure why it's not 20 ft,
but we can look at that to see. But why
why is neither block from this block
there's no setbacks.
So on North Queen Street parking within
20 ft of a crosswalk based on the
vehicle code. But that's not true
because on on Chess Street there's no
setback. Well, it's not it's not marked
everywhere, but that's just what the
vehicle code says. Just like you can't
park 15 ft from a fire hydrant, you
know, you have So, mine was the first
one on Queen Street to get this.
I'm sorry. My my block and my that
corner there was the first one to get
this on Queen Street. First to get what
Queen Street? The setbacks. The pavement
markings and the delineators.
The pavement parkings. The pavement
markings and the posts. I guess the
posts haven't gone into No, the p on the
streets. I mean, you've done it on many
intersections throughout the
city. I I don't know of any. On Ches
Street, it's right up to the crosswalk
and and and following block and James
Street, it's up to the crosswalk. I
mean, at the every location, it's, you
know, it's part of the vehicle code. So,
we try to emphasize it at certain
locations by putting those pavement
markings down, right? And as we do the
work and events, as we do that
enforcement as well.
Okay, I trust your opinion. My digging
in is it it doesn't do
anything. It takes up parking spaces.
That's what it does. It sets back
people. Now you have on Lemon Street,
you still
have two loading zones on Lemon Street
at two different
locations with no
businesses. Does that what happens
there? Does that make sense?
So what what locations are those? The
one at Smiley's Deli.
Well, that's a business. That's a
loading zone and it's a business. Pardon
me. Uh you had said that there were
loading zones where there were no
businesses. Yeah, it's no business
there. It's closed been closed for two
years.
Okay. What's the second location? And
the second one is at the apartment
building right across the street where
I'm at. They have a loading zone in the
back in the
garage. You go in the garage and you
load all your furniture up and it goes
up the
elevator. Why? Why is there two there?
There's only a corner store and a a hair
salon
there. And she take and she only has one
appointment a day and she you know her
her her customers like $3,000 a day. So
Sergeant, are you going to take a look
to see what the situation is for those?
Yeah, we can take a look at it. Uh I
mean if you see saw the pictures that I
put up there, you can see what's
happening to that loading zone. I mean
have people sleeping on the ground on
the Mr. Ser. That's fine. Uh I took I
took notes. Okay. Okay. Get those. But I
believe we're here to solve your problem
this evening. Okay. And I believe that's
what we Okay. Thank you very much.
Thanks. Thank Thank you for your time.
So, um, we we have a mo uh we haven't
yet created a motion
to have the report I'm sorry. I I don't
think we need I think we can just um
administrative say that this will be
dealt with administratively. Yes. And we
don't need to take action.
And it and it will be consistent with
the the loading zone somewhere in mid
block depending on what the report
indicates as well as confirmation of the
uh handicap station which I believe has
already been installed been installed.
Okay, Minnie, do you have all
that? Very good. Thank you very much,
Mrs. Thank you very much. Very kind.
Thank you.
So under this where it says considering
the request of the load zone, this is a
moot
request because it would be dealt with
administratively. The next item then is
item
11-2025. Consider the request of Martin
Keane to restrict parking on Abraham
Polite
Street, Abraham Polite Senior Avenue and
Cemetery Avenue.
No. Yes. Good afternoon. Um, have you
received the packet of information that
I gave to Mindy Gable? Yes, I have. It's
extensive. Have you all read it? I've
read much of it.
And what I what I'm finding though is
that it may be a again this may be a
situation that we as traffic commission
don't have jurisdiction because it is
not part of the public right of way.
Because it's not what part of the public
right of way. Well, actually it is. And
that's what I'm trying to to do with
that is show that it is a public street
and it has gone back and forth over 50
years that I've been involved with it
that is private or public. And I I don't
understand what the city's problem is
with it. If it's not if it's not a
public street, then really no street in
the city of Lancaster is public.
No, most of the streets in the city of
Lancaster are public, but this one for a
variety of of reasons, including some of
the information that you had submitted,
is indicated to not public street. And
we would not be able to act on it until
it is until or unless it is designated a
public street. So, we're we're it's not
that we won't do yay or nay. He said,
"We're not the right entity to which you
appeal to make sure that it is mapped as
a public
street." So, who do I go to? The city
has threatened has threatened to take us
to court. And I said, "Fine, take us to
court because I know we'll
win because it has to be a city street
because it's the Hamilton lots. If it's
not a city street, then streets such as
Christian, Cherry, Mifflin, those cannot
be city streets then because they fall
all under the same jurisdiction. The
original
layout of the
streets
before Pennsylvania was even a state. I
mean, that became that became a public
street in 1752.
The the un I guess the unfortunate thing
is that this one has been in contention
and we as traffic commission cannot take
action on it unless and until it is made
clear that it is designated as a public
street. So I I'm not in a position to
argue. Okay. Well, I get if if there's
proof that can be presented with a with
a ser I don't know survey and
certification that is so designated then
we can
act. But right now what you're making is
you're trying to make the case and we're
not the entity that adjudicates that
type of a case.
Well, okay. When I was talking with the
city's council for this, uh, Neil
Albert, we agreed that it was they
agreed it was a city street. Their only
contention was the width of the street,
the city at that point in time. That was
their only contention. And they have not
passed that on to you or no one seems to
know that. I mean, I will say that it
was
not documented that it was a city
street. That was an opinion, not
a not a a a set.
Well, then over the summer, why why did
the city patch some of the potholes?
It may have been a mistake. No, they've
always they've done it for years. I
think it's been a question of whether
it's public or private and the
documentation that you provided from the
former mayor and public works director
that it was private is what the city is
going with because that's the last
correspondence that was provided to you
related to the status of the street. So
knowing that the people current uh DPW
employees were not aware of that
correspondence and once we became aware
now we are treating it as a private
street until it is proven otherwise and
there are a number of those throughout
the city um that are either
uh private or shared alleys.
Okay. It'll tie up the traffic some of
the times then because we have to unload
tractor trailers. I mean, we've been
operating there for next year. Next year
will be our hundth year of operating
there. So, it'll just tie up the traffic
when we have done the tractor trailers.
What I would suggest is either through
your your solister or ours seek the
remedy. What it how do you get it
designated one way or the other? If it
becomes a public street then we can talk
about parking and how and where parking
can or cannot be restricted. But if it
is not public we cannot or if it is not
clear we
cannot say a or nay.
Okay. I'm very very sorry about that.
Okay. Um so then this this again it
seems that this is administrative
because we don't have
authority to do anything on this on this
particular item.
We could just deny just deny
because because of
jurisdiction deny for lack of
confirmation of jurisdiction.
Yeah. I make a motion to deny the
request of 11205.
It's a motion made. Is there a second?
Second.
Any further discussion?
All in favor? I. Any opposed? That
motion carries. Thank
you. So, the next new business item is
item
12-2025. consider the request of
concerns regarding oversized vehicles
parking on Fremont
Street. And that request is by this
issue.
Is this one been one that you had looked
at? No. No, I think Sergeant Summer can
provide. Sergeant, can you speak on this
one? Yes, I can. Um, so this this came
in um a couple different ways, but uh
nevertheless, we did as the police
department uh take a look at this. Um
the vehicles are tow trucks. Uh we
reached out I personally reached out to
the tow truck owner um advised them on
the oversized vehicle uh ordinance um in
the city of Lancaster uh which states
that these vehicles are not allowed to
park on the street between the hours of
10 p.m. and two excuse me and 6:00 a.m.
except for one hour at a time. Um we did
send out a representative of the
department to advise him um one night in
person. Um, tires were marked, came
back, vehicles were still parked,
tickets were issued. Um, this came, this
complaint came in from a neighbor who
also sent me photos of the vehicles
parked out front. Um, however, during
the daylight hours, um, before the hours
of 10 p.m., those vehicles being parked
on the street are legally parked. Um,
and this was relate to uh all parties
that the ordinance clearly states 1000
p.m. uh Monday through Friday and at
midnight on the weekends. Uh that the
vehicles are not allowed to be parked
other than 1 hour on the streets. These
are not commercial vehicles. They do not
exceed the weight of 26,000 lbs. Uh but
these vehicles do have a gross vehicle
weight and based on the way the
ordinance is written, gross vehicle
weight is what they are permitted to
tow. Um so if they exceed that gross
vehicle weight um all vehicles in
question.
So is it a is it a matter that there
needs to be signage here or how what's
the best way for it to be enforced? So
enforcement is only it's only permitted
based on the ordinance after 10 p.m.
Okay. So during the daytime as you see
the pictures here when the tow trucks
are parked they're legally parked. Um so
I said they do not fall under the
commercial vehicle um designation. So
you could post the, you know, no
commercial vehicle signs just as they're
posted in the 1100 block, but it
wouldn't apply to these particular
vehicles. So the best way to enforce is
either to have people constantly call
or have two or three blasts where
they're ticketed and get the message.
So the correspondence I had back and
forth was that it was resolved at least
for that period of time. Um like
speaking to the tow truck owners, they
were willing to move their vehicles,
have their small tow truck there parked
to the rear of the property as long as
it was uh parked on an approved pad for
parking within the uh the residents. Um
so at this point in time I hadn't heard
anything else from uh the person who had
initially uh lodged the
complaint. It would take some followup
if to see whether they're still having
an issue but again it's happening at
night. You know that's the time we can
actually you know bring any sort of
enforcement. Um and quite frankly people
just aren't up in the middle of the
night looking out the window to see if
there's a tow truck parked there. Um,
council member, you had you had brought
part of this to our attention. I think
you had reached out to see if there were
uh residents who were willing to come
and speak.
Yes. But I didn't um I would have to
like schedule for her to come in to
speak because she does work. So, she's
not able to come like around this time,
but she did bring it to my attention.
Um, and the elderlys that are living
on the opposite direction that that the
neighbor question was. They're elderly
and they had to get to garages in order
to
avoid the constant trying to get parking
because those tow trucks are there
and but it seems like it's more like
it's an enforcement issue. Um which
means
that and please correct me if this is
not the appropriate strategy. um that in
the short term since they are not
illegally
parked ex
during during that
day when they are illegally parked one
needs to call for them to be ticketed.
Okay.
And hopefully that gets the message
across that they're not to be parking
there when they're not supposed to be
parking there. Correct. I would say that
would be um our only course of action at
this point in time. uh outside of you
know a new ordinance being rewritten.
Um and that's if there were a new
ordinance rewritten it would have to
address this kind of a situation in
several other locations. We would have
to talk about the category of truck. It
would have to be cityide different um a
different threshold of weight category
which we I don't believe we have that
separate weight category at this time.
So it's a matter of
enforcement. She's Do you have a sense
of clarity of what kind of enforcement?
Well, if they have it parked there when
the majority of the community that comes
home from work, then they do have to
move it in order for them to have the
space there to park.
[Music]
So, I would say they'd have to move it
out of the area in order for them to
have access to parking. Yes, that's not
that's not something we can enforce
because they're legally parked at that
point in time. Like I said, it's Well,
isn't the size I mean, I know that
there's a certain weight and size that
they're not supposed to be parked there.
So, the over the oversized again, the
way the the ordinance is written, the
overweight and oversized, it it is about
the weight. It's not the overall
dimension of the vehicle. It's the it's
the weight of the vehicle. Um these
vehicles are not blocking any sight
lines parked near a stop sign or
anything like that causing a hazard or
prevent people from seeing signage. Um
they're they're just parked and I know
it's inconvenient and it's it's not
courteous. Um but again, it's not
illegal either. I will let her know
then and we'll see if anything else
additional we can do to make changes.
Um, I think part of it may be having
clarity in the immediate neighborhood of
what to do and when the these vehicles
are allowed, when they are not allowed,
so
that one gets into the right rhythm, but
also enforcing the trucks not being
there when they're not supposed to be
there. so
that
there's greater flexibility in terms of
parking availability
and and that information again was was
provided. Um I'm just curious as to um
how recent uh these this this complaint
has kind of come to your attention just
because we like I said we we did put a
decent amount of effort into resolving
this problem. I think she said that she
had forwarded to um Mr. Campbell a year
ago, but so this is a continual. Okay.
Because I I like I said, I I spoke to
her January um this year of this year.
So the last eight weeks and and like I
said, we did I don't have the dates on
when we issue tickets, but uh we did
issue tickets on all of our tow trucks.
um which um the the vehicle owner called
me um upset about it obviously uh
responded to the station, spoke to the
death sergeant um Sergeant Funigger also
spoke to um the tow tow truck owner
because they are one of our approved
towers um and advised them on what the
ordinance is and what the expectation
was. So um I don't mind following up
with her to see if the problem still is
persistent or if it hasn't been
resolved. That would be great if that
would be great. Um, and maybe letting
her know that they that they were
ticketed because maybe she feels like
nobody has been listening to her. Well,
she was aware because I know then there
was the the call came back about one of
her vehicles which was legally parked as
well. So, um, it just became a back and
forth between, you know, neighbors at
that point in time. But like I said, we
we did our best to try to handle the
situation at that point in time based on
the uh parameters that were able to
function in. Okay. So, it would be it
would be greatly appreciated if you can
follow up with the third and see if that
situation has changed now that the
weather is changing. It may be something
that needs to be repeated in order to u
reinforce to people that they shouldn't
uh be parking here.
Yes.
when they when they're not allowed to be
parking there um but get into the right
rhythm of it. Correct.
Thank you. So, is there any further
action to be taken on that particular
item?
Not administrative. It's
administratively
addressed. Hold on a second.
[Music]
So this this one's being addressed
administratively as
well. No action is
necessary. So that completes our new
business action agenda. The next is the
consent agenda. And traditionally what
we've done is looked at each of these
items. Um, and there's one item
13-2025 signs having been tentatively
approved or installed. Item
14-20245 following signs have been
removed. Item 15
2022 conditional temporary parking
permits have been issued by LPA and item
16-2025 conditional temporary parking
permits have been asked for continuence.
We often either take them individually
or as a
group as a single motion unless there's
and to my recollection there has not
been a challenge
uh for any of the addresses
listed. So I'd be either waiting for a
motion for one of them or a motion for
all. A motion for all.
A motion has been introduced for all. Is
there a second? I'll second. Sorry.
motion and a second. Is there any
discuss further
discussion? All in favor? I The motion
carries. So, all the consent agenda
items have been passed. Is there any any
additional business that needs to come
before the commission?
Um, having said that, the uh the agenda
of the traffic commission for March 11th
has been completed. Do I hear a motion
to adjourn?
So move.
This motion ends. A second. All in
favor? I. Motion carries. Thank you very
much. 4:38 p.m.
Yes.